<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The continual follovving of the French king vpon the Duke of Parma, the Duke of Guise, the Duke of Maine, and their armies From the seuenteenth of Aprill, vntill the 20. of the same month. Togither with the honourable attempts of Sir Roger Williams and his men.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02991</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116648</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851864</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851864</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17157</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02991)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17157)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1309:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The continual follovving of the French king vpon the Duke of Parma, the Duke of Guise, the Duke of Maine, and their armies From the seuenteenth of Aprill, vntill the 20. of the same month. Togither with the honourable attempts of Sir Roger Williams and his men.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and Edvvard White, and are to be solde at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1592]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A continuation of STC 11260--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Williams, Roger, --  Sir, 1540?-1595.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:17157:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>engraving of Saint George, armoured on horseback, killing the dragon with a lance</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17157:1"/>
            <p>THE CONTINVAL FOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovving of the French king vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>on the Duke of Parma, the Duke of</hi> Guiſe, the Duke of Maine, and their Armies. <hi>From the ſeuenteenth of Aprill, vntill</hi> the 20. of the ſame month. Togither with the Honourable attempts of Sir <hi>Roger Williams</hi> and his men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and Edvvard White, and are to be ſolde at the ſigne of the Gunne.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:17157:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17157:2"/>
            <head>The continuall following of the <hi>French king vpon the Duke of Parma, the</hi> Duke of Guiſe, the duke of Maine, and their Armies, from the 17. of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill, vntill the 20. of the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He 17. of this moneth the king departed from <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleca velea:</hi> vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Duke of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> beſieged <hi>Caw debeck</hi> hoping to encloſe hym there, but that morning he was aduertiſed of the yeelding of that place, and that the Duke had encamped himſelf in the plain field one league from <hi>Euetote,</hi> where he had en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched himſelf. And the Duke of <hi>Guyes</hi> and <hi>Mayne,</hi> with two thouſand horſe, and a thouſand and two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred foote at <hi>Euetote:</hi> Wherevpon the king marched towards them withall his troopes in battell ray, and tenne peeces of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> till within three quarters of a leagu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17157:3"/> there cauſing his armie to ſtay. He with 500. horſe made forward to diſcouer his ennemies order of encamping: the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> ſhewed himſelfe with a thouſand horſe, thinking to driue vs to retire: but the king charged his men with two troopes, and made them retire into their quarter with diſhonour, and the loſſe of <hi>Monſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Countenaw:</hi> who was taken priſoner, and did aſſure the king, that the Duke <hi>de Parma</hi> was but newly aduertiſed of his comming, and that he did not thinke that the K. durſt abide him: which pleaſed the king verie well.</p>
            <p>And further he ſaid that the Duke dyd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue to giue the King battayle, wherevnto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the kinge prepared himſelfe againſt the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, the ſayde next day, the kinge ſeeing that the Enemie came not forward, reſolued to take by force the village of <hi>Euetote,</hi> and to lodge there in deſpite of the enemie, or elſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine them to fight.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon he ſente out Curaces and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebuſſes vpon horſſebacke, to obſerue what countenance the enimy kept, who as then were comming on with horſſe and foot: but percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that the kinge came, with a reſolution to charge them, they retired, ſhamefully forſaking their quarter and ſetting fire on it, and went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye in great diſorder, vntill they were come vnto the Duke de <hi>Parma</hi> his quarter.</p>
            <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> followed them and killed diuerſe,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17157:3"/> and tooke ſome Gentlemen priſoners, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the reſte, the Baron <hi>de la Chaſtre,</hi> the Duke de <hi>Maine</hi> was almoſte taken, his horſſe being cleane out of breath.</p>
            <p>In this conflict there weare of them aboute foure ſcore ſlaine: that day wee lodged at <hi>Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tote,</hi> and the villages beyond, which we hadde woon of the enimie within three quarters of a League off the Dukes trenches, wherat the D. was much aſtoniſhed, and imagined he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied by the French. The xix. day we offered them manie ski<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſhes, but the Duke was very coole and would not ſtir.</p>
            <p>The Kinge as well to come by victuall him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by ſaint <hi>Vallarie</hi> and <hi>Diep,</hi> as alſo to hinder the comming of any to the enimie, remooued from <hi>Euetote</hi> and came towards <hi>Newhauen.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wee were lodged, the enemie laide an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcado for vs, and ſent ſome of his horſemen to tole vs on. Therevpon the kinge ſent for ſir <hi>Roger Williams</hi> to come vnto him with two hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred Muskets, and an hundred and fiftie Pikes, which were preſentlie charged by fiue Cornets of <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> whoe were ſo well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, that two of their Coronets were taken.</p>
            <p>Some of the Commanders of thoſe horſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were killed, and many hurt in the meane time vi. hundred Musketers and Corſlets of the enemie, which were alſo backed by other companies maintained a hotte skirmiſh with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17157:4"/> our men, but in the end the enemie was forced to retire with ſhame and loſſe, there were in this conflict fortie Engliſh hurt, and eight ſlain. The king doth greatly exalt the Engliſh, and fir <hi>Roger Williams</hi> for their valor ſhewed at this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, who haue alſo gotten therein great good ſpoile and booties of the enemies.</p>
            <p>The Gallion of <hi>Roane</hi> was lately taken by ſome ſhips that lie in the riuer, and which doth alſo hinder the comming of victuall vnto the campe.</p>
            <p>There was a letter of the Duke, vnto the king of Spaine intercepted, wherein he rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the miſerie that he is in, for want of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſtrength to meete the king, and his great want of victuals, and the ſmall meanes he hath to make a good retreate.</p>
            <p>He alſo complaineth of the duke <hi>de Maine</hi> &amp; the other french ſaying, that they haue in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner betraied him, &amp; concludes that he cannot retire without fighting, and haſſarding the loſſe of his armie,</p>
            <p>He hath receiued a ſhot in the arme, and is like as his Phyſition ſaith, to loſe it: for althogh the hurt of it ſelfe be not daungerous, yette by reaſon of diſtemperature and other accidentes which commonlie followe vppon ſuch hurts they ſtand in great doubt of it, he is carried in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tter and cannot yet ride on horſſeback. The king is reſolued to aſſaile him in his trenches, if
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17157:4"/> he will not otherwiſe accept of battayle.</p>
            <p>We feare nothing but that hee will ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the night. The kinge hath at this time 2600. Frenche Curaces, and 800. Harquebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers on horſſebacke, beſides three thouſande French footmen which are dailie expected: he hath alſo ſent for all his garriſons round about him, and the longer the duke dooth ſtaie, the more forces the king will haue.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17157:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17157:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
